اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراً
Sa’ad Ibn Abi Waqas رضي الله عنه sent a representative, to speak with Rustum(رستم),
the army general of the Persian Empire.
Rabie Ibn Amir رضي الله عنه was one the chosen by the Sa'ad(سعد) to go and meet with Rustum(رستم).
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) he was very poor man, so he was riding a short-legged, hairy horse
and his sword was wrapped in an old piece of cloth.
He didn’t even have a proper sheath for his sword.
And his spear, the blade was tight to the stick with also some cloth.
So, his whole assortment of weapons was messed up.
And he was wearing clothes that are very inexpensive, modest.
Now, the Persians have prepared for this meeting.
It’s a high level meeting between Rustum(رُسْتُم) and representatives of the Muslim army.
So, they had Persian rugs, they had the throne set for Rustum(رُسْتُم)
and this throne was gold plated or possibly it was even pure gold
and he had a dress of brocade on, and it was threaded with gold threads all over.
And they had the royal guards on both sides of the carpet,
which Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) was suppose to walk over.
It’s the proper protocol of such a high level meeting
and Romans were used to this, and Persians were used to this,
and these two nations were at each other's throats.
So, it was something, that was customary for them to do
and now since, they were dealing with Muslims they thought that protocols shouldn’t change.
So, the proper way of coming in,
is that Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) should come on a very nice handsome horse,
dressed in very expensive clothes.
He should be accompanied by guards or at least group of advisors with him.
He should then come down of his horse and walk on this carpet in a formal way,
and then he come and sit under Rustum(رُسْتُم).
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) is coming on his short legged horse,
and he goes straight onto the rugs riding his horse
so they stopped him
he carried on, he didn’t listen,
he carried on and then he goes and tears apart two pillows that were there,
and he ties his horse to those pillows and then he is walking with his weapons.
So the guards stopped him at the entrance, to the place where Rustum(رُسْتُم) was sitting.
They said: You're not allowed to go in, with your arms.
He said: Well, I didn’t come here on my own but you are the ones, who invited me,
so you either you let me in, with my arms or I am going to leave.
They went and told Rustum(رُسْتُم), he said, let him come in.
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) is walking with confidence and he is holding his spear
with the blade pointing downwards and he is poking the rugs and he is making holes in them.
So, you can imagine that he is walking towards Rustum(رُسْتُم) and Rustum is seeing this
and Rabie(ربيع) is stabbing his special Persian rug with every step that he takes.
Because Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) didn’t want all of this pump, he didn’t want this show,
and he was uncomfortable being there.
They have done all those preparations to meet him.
And here is the guest poking through the rugs with his spear.
So, that was the initial shock.
Rustum(رُسْتُم) said;
"مَا جَآءَ بِكُمْ"
Why did you come to our land?
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) said;
إنَّ اللهَ بْتَعَثَنَا، لِنُخْرِجَ الْعِبَادْ
مِنْ عِبَادَةِ الْعِبَادْ، إِلَى عِبَادَةِ رَبِّى الْعِبَادْ
وَمِنْ ضِيْقِّ الدُّنْيَا إِلَى سَعْتِ دُّنْيَا وَالْآخِرَةْ
وَمِنْ جَوْرِالْأَدْيَانْ إِلَى سَعْتِ الْإِسْلَام
There is more, to what the eye can see,
don’t make an impression on Rabie(ربيع) because of the clothes that he has on
or his short legged horse
but wait until, you see him speak.
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) said: Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has sent us to deliver you,
from worshiping the creation, to worshiping the Creator of the creation,
and to deliver you from the constriction of this world,
to the vastness of this world and the afterlife
and from the oppression of religions, to the justice of Islam.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has sent us to save you from worshiping each others.
What you are doing now, this servitude that exist among you,
Rustum(رُسْتُم) is sitting up on the throne rest of you sitting on the floor, the slavery, the servitude.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has sent us to deliver you out of that,
to save you from this, from worshiping creation,
whether this creation is a man or a stone,
whether it is an animal or a planet,
Allah has sent us to save people deliver them from that to worshiping the Creator of everything,
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has sent us to deliver you from the constriction of this life.
This Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is narrow, to the vastness of this life and the afterlife.
As a Muslim, you have a broad perspective, you start seeing things in a different light.
See without Qur’an, you are living for today,
you eat to live and you live to eat.
But when you recite Qur'an, it starts from the time of Adam(آدم)
and it ends with people entering into Jannah(جنة) and Naar(ألنار).
You have the entire time span, of the creation in front of your eyes.
It starts in fact, from before the creation of Adam(آدم).
It starts with the Khalaq(خلق) of Assamawaat Wal-Ardh(السموات والارض)
and then you go to the story of Adam(آدم),
then you move to the story of Idrees(إدريس) and Noah(نوح)
and then you go on to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Bani Israel(بني اسرائيل),
Musa عليه السّلام, Eesa عليه الاسلام
and before that Ibrahim عليه الاسلام and Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), Ishaq(إسحاق).
It tells you about the nations of before, Firaun(فرعون),
it tell's you about Qaum Salih(قوم الصالح), Qaum Hood(قوم هود), Qaum Shoaib(الشّعيب قوم)
and then it tells you about the time Muhammad ﷺ and then it talks about the future.
It talks about the Day of Judgment, death, Al-Hissab(الحساب), the accounting the reckoning
and then it talks about Jannah(جنة) and Naar(ألنار), so you know everything.
Just look at how broad your perspective is compare to somebody who doesn’t know Qur’an,
somebody who is not a Muslim.
So, Islam delivers person out of narrowness of this world,
Ibn Taymiah(إبن تيمية), when they were threatening him with jail
and one time threatening him with execution, and….
Ibn Taymiah(إبن تيمية) said: What can you do with me?
My Jannah(جنة) is in my heart,
if you take me to jail, I will make Zikr(زكر) of Allah,
if you exile me out of my land, I will make Tafakkur(تفكّر), contemplate in the creation of Allah,
if you execute me, I would be a Shaheed(شهيد).
What can you do with me?
"ما يفعلوآضائبى"
What can you do?
Because I am not limited to this Duniyah(دنيا)
I am living for Al-Akhirah(الآخرة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
عَجَبًا لِّأَمْرِ الْمُؤمِنِ إِنَّ أَمْرَه’ كُلَّ لَه’ خَيْرٌ
إِنْ أصَابَتْه’ سَرَّاءُ شَكَرَ فَكَانَتْ خَيْرَا لَّهْ
وَإِنْ أَصَابَتْهُ ضَرَّاءُ صَبرَ، فَكَانَتْ خَيْرًا لَّهْ
وَلَيْسَ ذَلِكَ لِأَحَدٍ إِلَّا لِمُؤْمِنِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying: "I am amazed with the situation of the believer,
if something good happens to him,
he thanks Allah and that's good for him,
if something bad happens to him, he is patient and that’s good for him
and that happens to no one but to the believer".
It’s a win, win situation, you can never lose.
Something good you say Alhamdulillah(ألحمدلله) you rewarded for that.
You are enjoying the good and you are being rewarded for that.
If something bad happens, you say Alhamdulillah(ألحمدلله)
and you are patient and you accept the Qadha(قضى) of Allah.
You accept it as something being ordained by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and you say:
ألحمدالله رب العلمين
And you move on and you will be rewarded for that patience.
However, somebody who doesn’t have Eeman(ايمان)
if something good will happen, they will say because I am very intelligent,
I am skilled, I am knowledgeable and I know how to do things right.
If something bad happens, I have bad luck.
This is because of you, you did it to me.
So, it’s a lose, lose situation.
وَمِنْ جَوْرِالْأَدْيَانْ إِلَىِ عَدْلِ الْإِسْلَام
"From oppression of religions to the justice of Islam"
Rabie(ربيع) is saying that every other religion is oppressive.
Now, ask Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) about the names of the religions of the earth, he wouldn’t known them.
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر), the Bedouin coming out of Arabia,
he doesn’t know about other religions, he wasn’t a student of comparative religion.
But he has Eeman(ايمان) and Trust in Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and that Islam is the truth,
and that Muhammadﷺ is the seal of Prophets,
so he is speaking on behalf of every religion,
every religion is oppressive except Islam.
So, we are here, to deliver you that into the religion of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Rustum(رُسْتُم) said: You use to eat dead animals,
you were so hungry, you use to run after dogs in desert".
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) said;
We offer you three options,
if you become Muslim, we will leave you and your land and people alone.
If you refuse then you pay us Jizya(جزية), in a state of submission,
if you refuse then the sword is between us and you.
Rustum(رُسْتُم) said: You need to give us time, to think about it.
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) said: We will give you three days.
Rustum(رُسْتُم) said: No! We need more than that.
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) said:
"The Sunnah(سنة), the way of Muhammadﷺ is that, we give our enemy three days to think about it
and we will visit you during those three days, on the fourth day, we will start fighting.
Rustum(رُسْتُم) wanted more time to send letters to the Emperor to seek advice,
from the noble men and elders of their Empire but he had only three days.
So, on the second day, Al-Mugheera Bin Sho'ba(ألّمغيره بن شعبة) went to met with Rustum(رُسْتُم),
and he came in straight, and he sat, on the throne.
The throne was big, so he sat next to Rustum(رُسْتُم),
so the guards came to pull him down,
you are not suppose to sit on the same level as Rustum(رُسْتُم).
Al-Mugheera(ألمغيرة) said: That is because, you are the people, who worship each other
but that is not how we Muslims treat each other,
we treat each other with equality.
See the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم are giving the Kuffar(كفار) lessons
because they are living those meanings.
See the Sahabah(صحابه) were not just talking talks,
they were talking about things that, they were practicing.
They were practicing, what they are preaching and that’s, why?
Their words had such a strong influence on the listeners.
You know, At-Tabri(ألطبري) talks about how
the words of Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) and Al-Mugheera Bin Sho'ba(ألّمغيره بن شعبة) affected, the low class,
who were there, the servants and the soldiers and security guards,
when they heard the statements of Muslims
and how the Muslims treat each other with equality
and the fact, that there are not here invade the lands of others, just for love of power,
they are doing it for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, to save people from darkness to light.
That left a strong impression on them.
They were thinking about Islam even before the battle started.
Why? Because when you practice something it has a stronger influence,
then when you preach something, that you are not practicing.
It is said that one of the Salaf(سلف), one of the early scholars,
people came up to him and said: That people are owning too many slaves
and it's becoming problem so, we want you to encourage freeing slaves.
So, first Jumu'ah(جمعه) came he didn’t talk about it,
second Juma’ah(جمعه) he didn’t talk about it,
third Jumu'ah(جمعه) he didn’t talk about it.
They said: May be he forgot.
But before they go and visit him, on fourth Jumu'ah(جمعه) he did talked about it.
And he encouraged people to free slaves
and they say the people left the Masjid(مسجد) and they were freeing the slaves left and right.
So, they told him, how come you waited for four Jumu'ah(جمعه) to give this Khutba(خطبة)?
He said: Because I didn’t want to ask the people to do something that I am not doing myself.
So, I gathered enough money to buy a slave myself and then I freed that slave
and that’s, when I stood on the pulpit and told people to do it,
because I don’t want to be of those who,
أَتَأْمُرُونَ النَّاسَ بِالْبِرِّ وَتَنْسَوْنَ أَنْفُسَكُمْ
Do you command others to do good, while you forget doing it yourselves.
I want to be of those who do what they ask others to do.
The battle of Al-Qadisiyyah(ألقادسية) began and it was a long battle.
Remember that the reputation of the Persians was that of, very strong fighters.
And they were putting up a very stiff resistance in front of the Muslim forces. .
So, the battle of Al-Qadisiyyah(ألقادسية) lasted for few days, four days actually.
They start fighting in the morning and carries on fighting until darkness
and they stop when it's dark.
The First day was called Yaum Armaas(يوم أرماث)
and Sa'ad Bin Abi Waqas(سعدبن أبي وقاص) had some injuries and he had a back problem.
He had a severe back pain,
so he was unable to participate himself in the fighting, even though he was Ameer(أمير) of the army,
so he had to stay in a high place where he can oversee the battleground
and give instructions but he himself wasn't able to participate.
He told the Muslims to make four Takbiraat(تكبيرات) and to charge at the fourth Takbira(تكبيرة).
Before that he had the Qari(قارى), the Qari(قارى) of the army,
every army would have a Qari(قارى), a reciter of the Qur’an
and this Qari(قارى) would go around reciting Surat-Ul Anfaal(سورة ألأنفال).
Surat-Ul Anfaal(سورة ألأنفال) is a Surat-Ul Qitaal(سورة القتال).
So, he would go around reciting the Surah(سورة) to everybody,
obviously this was a large army, so one person cannot recite it, at the same time to everybody.
They would not be able to hear him, so he would have to go around
and recite the Surah(سورة) and this would inspire the fighters to fight.
Because this is the Surah(سورة) of Qitaal(قتال), Surat-Ul Anfaal(سورة ألأنفال).
So, that prepared them emotionally, it talks about Shahadah(شهادة), it talks about fighting,
it talks about the sin of retreating, it talks about the Ghanaem(غنائم),
it talks about the victories of the time Muslims in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ, in Ghazwa-Badr(غزوةالبدر)
and the fighting started.
What the army of Faris(فارس) did was that they sent fourteen elephants
to charge against one segment of the Muslim army.
So, they didn’t attack Muslim army at once,
what they did is, they focused on one segment and they sent fourteen elephants.
And with each elephant you have four thousand soldiers, because
each four thousand soldier would have on elephant with them,
so we are talking about huge number
and they charged against Bajeela(بجيلة).
Now, the Muslim army was divided according to their tribes.
So you had Banu Asad(بنوأسد), Banu Tamim(بنوأسد), Bajeela(بجيلة), An-Nakha’a(ألنخة),
every tribe would be separate.
The reason why they were separated according to their tribes
is because, this will inspire them to fight.
When they are separated according to their tribes,
whenever there is weakness, you could tell, where it's coming from?
So, you will know that the weakness is coming from that tribe.
This particular tribe are not doing their job
and this way people could be held accountable.
However, when you have the infantry or cavalry is mixed,
then who could you hold accountable for the weakness that occurs?
But when its according to the tribes, every tribes doesn’t want reputation to be destroyed.
So, they would make sure that Muslims are not defeated because of them.
However, here we have a huge army attacking one small tribe.
And it was such a powerful strike that it just completely pushed them back.
So, Sa’ad bin Abi Waqas(سعدبن أبي وقاص) asked some of the other tribes
to rush to the support and rescue, of their brothers,
so Bannu Asad(بنوأسد) jumped in.
One of the leading members of Bannu Asad(بنوأسد),
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) and look at how things turnaround was Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي).
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي) was a well-known fighter in the time of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة)
he was a strong fighter in the pre Islamic era.
However, out of nationalistic pride,
he claimed to be Prophet in the time of Muhammadﷺ, he claimed to be a Prophet.
And he was the leader of the one of the armies of Al-Murtadeen(ألمرتدين).
However, when he was defeated by Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he became a Muslim again
and later on, he would play a vital role in the Ghazwat(غزوات) in time of Umar Ibn Khattab رضي الله عنه.
So, here we have somebody who claims to be a Prophet but then turns around makes Tauba(توبة)
and helps the Muslims.
And this tells you the Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ can forgive any sin.
I mean, what sin can be greater than claiming to be a Prophet?
Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي) encouraged his men and told them, you are called Asd(أسد),
Asd(أسد) mean lion, it mean lion.
He said: You were given this name, so that you would be like lions.
And he would speak to them and encouraging them
and they were very helpful infact, five hundred of them were killed.
The day of Armaas(أرماس) was over, the dead and the injured were carried, to the camp.
And who is taking care of the hospital, if we would call it so?
The women.
The women were the ones, taking care of the injured all of the casualties,
they were the ones, who would administer the healing procedure,
they are the ones, who would feed them, they are the one who would nurse the injured,
and also the women did something else and that is bury the dead.
So, they would be, the ones digging the graves, and burying the dead.
So, the women in those days played an important role with the Muslim Ummah(امة).
They were not excluded completely put on standby.
No! They played a very important role, and it even involve physical work,
I mean digging graves and carrying the bodies, and putting them, it's not something that is, easy to do.
But that role was delegated to the woman whether they were Sahabiyat(صحابيات) or Tabi'aat(تابيعات).
The second day was Yaum Aghwaas(يوم أغواث),
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) had asked for reinforcements to come from Ash-Sham(ألشام).
He wanted the army of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) that went from Iraq to Ash-Sham(ألشام) to go back.
For those of you, who attended our series of talks on Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
you would remember we talked about a story of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
rushing from Iraq to Syria to rescue the Muslims, before the Battle of Yarmook(يرموك).
Now, however, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was asking Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) to send that army back
and that army was about twelve thousand soldiers.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) did send the army back he kept Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) with him.
He wants Khalid(خالد) to stay.
And that army was sent and it was lead by Hishaam Ibn Abi Waqas(هشام إبن أبي وقاص),
the brother of Sa’ad Bin Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص)
and was accompanied by a man, whom Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
His voice alone is equal to a thousand soldiers,
and this man is the great Sahabi(صحابي) Al-Qa'qaa Ibn Amr(ألقعقاع إبن عمرو).
Al-Qa'qaa(ألقعقاع) he had a very deep and loud voice, his voice in battle,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) says, it's worth of one thousand soldiers.
Al-Qa'qaa(ألقعقاع) was the first one to arrive.
He arrived in a small group hundred or so.
So, what he did in order to encourage the Muslims and raise their moral,
he didn’t come with his hundred men at once, he split them into groups of ten
and told them to go one after another, so the Muslims keep on seeing those groups coming
and they would think that we are getting an endless flow of reinforcements.
So, Al-Qa'qaa(ألقعقاع) arrives and he just enters into the battleground
and he is playing around with his spear, in his hand.
He just immediately, arrives goes into the battleground without taking any rest
even though he came all the way from Syria to Iraq.
He arrives there when the battle was already ragging.
And he enters into the battleground dancing with his spear in front of the Muslims.
And then he challenges the enemy to send out a Mubariz(مبارز),
it's called Mubariza(مبارزة), dueling.
It is one against one, one on one.
So Al-Qa'qaa(ألقعقاع) stands in front of the Muslim army and he calls the enemy to send out Mubariz(ألمبارز).
So, they sent out one of the five leaders
because Al-Qa'qaa(ألقعقاع) is an important leader among the Muslim army,
they sent out to him somebody of his equivalent status.
Al-Qa'qaa(ألقعقاع) killed him, they sent the second one, he killed him again,
so he killed two of the five major leaders of the army.
Al-Qa'qaa Ibn Amr(ألقعقاع إبن عمرو) carried on that day
and he played a very important role as an individual not with his reinforcement,
as an individual in weakening the enemy, on the second day.
Albaa Bin Jahash Al-Ajli(علباء بن جحش العجلي) he also asked for Al-Mubariza(ألمبارزة)
so both he and his opponent struck each other,
he hit his opponent and open his chest then he cut his lungs.
So, the man fell down dead, while he was hit in the stomach, so his intestines came out,
his gut just spilled out.
So, he fell down and he tried to put his intestines back.
So, he called one of the Muslim soldiers,
and he told him can you put my intestine back into my stomach please.
So, he put them in his stomach and then he wraps something around his stomach
and he stood up because he wanted to carry on fighting.
He barely made thirty steps before he fell down dead.
But Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) even though he is in that extreme pain and just imagine,
you know! I think some of you, now having a nausea, just because, I mentioned that.
It's, you know! Imagine you have your stomach, your guts, just spilling in front of you,
you would want to be rescued, to the nearest hospital as soon as possible.
He said: Just put them back, I want to carry on.
That tells you how attached they were to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and how attached they were to Shahadah(شهادة).
That's why we keep on saying these men were on different level.
Al-Khansaa(ألخنساء) was the one of the greatest women poetess,
she called her four sons, all of them men of fighting age
and she started narrating to them poetry encouraging them
to give their lives for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
at the end of the day, none of them came back.
All of the four died and she was so happy making poetry praising them.
The third day Amwass(عمواس),
the elephants, the only cure that Muslims has against them to cut down,
the ropes that were holding the saddles,
if we can call it a saddle.
So, the elephants would be left without anybody on top of them.
So, what the enemy did is.
Now, they surrounded the elephants with security.
Security guards, to protect the elephants,
because the elephants were playing a major role in the Persian army.
So, now since, they were surrounded with guards, it's becoming very difficult for the Muslims to cut down the ropes.
So Sa’ad Bin Abi Waqas(سعدبن أبي وقاص), he went to Bannu Tamim(بني تميم)
and he said: O Bannu Tamim(بني تميم) do you have a solution for this?
Is there anything that you could do?
And he is going to the different tribes and telling them somebody come up with suggestion to get rid of this danger.
We have been crushed because of these elephants.
They are just rolling over the soldiers, crushing them under their feet.
So, one man said: "If you want to stop the elephants then strike their eyes
and cut their trunks and lips
that would completely neutralize these elephants".
So, they decided to give it a try, and they started attacking the elephants.
The way they would do it is.
A group of them would attack, some of them would get the security guards busy
and then two of them would attack, with their spears and hit the elephant in his eye.
They tried that and it did work.
The elephant obviously, is blind now and it doesn’t know in which direction to go,
so some of these elephants carried on killing Muslims
and some of them carried on killing enemy soldiers.
So, the elephants just went crazy but at least now, it wasn’t all directed against the Muslims.
Amr Bin Maadi-Akrab(عمرو بن معديكرب) another one who committed, Riddah(ردة)
and was now allowed to join in the armies, he told his people,
he said: Listen Bannu Zabeed(بنوزبيد)! I am going to leave right now,
if you wait the time it takes to slaughter a camel, you will find me dead,
if you come before that you might find me alive fighting the enemy.
He is saying, that I am going to go straight into the heart of the enemy army.
So, he went alone,
after a short while, they said: We need to go and see our man and if he is still alive?
They went and they were amazed to see,
Amr Bin Maadi-Akrab(عمرو بن معديكرب), Wallahu Alam(والله أعلم) it's from At-Tabri(ألطبري),
it's amazing story but I am going to mention it.
They said, that he had a horse and his horse was killed, so what he did,
the man who was fighting against him killed his horse and he pursued him
and he grabbed the legs of his horse and the horse couldn’t move.
So, Amr Bin Maadi-Akrab(عمرو بن معديكرب) is holding the back legs, of this horse
and soldier on the top it is trying to hit the Ma'adi Akrib(معديكرب) from behind but he cannot reach him.
And when he saw reinforcement coming to help him, so this soldier just ran away.
So, Amr Bin Maadi-Akrab(عمرو بن معديكرب) took away his horse and carried on fighting.
But to have one man hold a horse and horse cannot move its quite, it's some power.
Then we have Lailat Al-Hareer(ليلة الهرير) this is the fourth day,
the fighting carried on, until night time, the fighting carried on until midnight.
And it was the toughest day of Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية)
and that is when the enemy was putting up a last attempt.
And at the end, Al-Qa'qa' Ibn Amr(ألقعقاع بن عمرو) felt that
they are pushing themselves to the limits and that they are almost going to break.
So, he and a group of strong men, decided to charge and just slice the enemy
and go straight to the camp of Rustum(رُسْتُم).
They did that and they reached to the camp of Rustum(رُسْتُم), the actual camp
and when Rustum(رُسْتُم) saw them, he ran away
but then one of the Muslim soldiers pursued him and was able to kill him,
and that was the end of the Battle of Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية).
The enemy was Hundred and Twenty Thousand strong, the Muslim army was Thirty Thousand,
and out of those 30,000, Eight Thousand Five Hundred died as Shaheed(شهيد).
So, you had huge number of Shuhadaa(شهداء) in Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية).
It was one of the toughest battles that the Muslims fought.
Sa'ad Ibn Abi Waqas رضي الله عنه sent a letter to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
giving him a good news.
He said: Now than Allah, granted us victory over the Persians
and treated them in the way in which he had treated their co-religionist, who preceded them.
Victory came after a long fight and violent upheaval,
they confronted the Muslims with an army such as, had never been seen before.
Allah didn’t allowed them to benefit from this but rather,
He deprived them of it and gave it over to the Muslims.
The Muslims pursued them on the canals, on the edge of the thicket and on the roads.
Sa'ad Bin Obaid(سعدبن عبيد) the Qur’an reader
and so and so and so and so were killed from among the Muslims.
The Qur'an reader, the Qari(قاري) was killed,
also killed were Muslims whom we do not know, but Allah knows them.
When night fell they were whispering the Qur'an humming like bees,
they were lions among men and the real lions did not resemble them.
Those who died from among them were not superior, to those who survived
except by the virtue of martyrdom which had not been decreed for the later."
The Muslims immediately after that went for Al-Madain(ألمدائن),  Al-Madain(ألمدائن) was the capital
Al-Madain(ألمدائن) was opened
they carried on and they fought in the battle of Jalola(جلولاء)
and then they went to Tastur(تستر), and they opened Tastur(تستر).
The battle of Tastur(تستر) was a tough battle.
So, the Muslims went to Al-Bara'a Bin Malik(ألبراء بن مالك),
and they told him to make a Dua(دُعَا) for them
because Al-Bara'a Bin Malik(ألبراء بن مالك) was Mustajaab-Ud-Dawah(مستجاب الدعوة)
his Dua(دُعَا) was accepted.
Al-Bara’a(ألبراء) was companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he was a very poor man, very simple.
But he was very decent, truthful and honest
and had so much love for Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and His Messenger, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
رُبَّ أَشْعَثْ أَغْبَرْإِذَا أَقْسَمَ عَلى الله لَأ أبَرَّهْ
"There is a man with unkempt hair and he has dust over his clothes
but when he makes an oath Allah would fulfill that oath."
So, for example, if he says in the name of Allah, this is going to happen,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will make that thing happen because He loves him so much.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said: And One of these men is Al-Bara'a(ألبراء).
Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) was such a strong fighter with no fear in his heart.
However, he had so much courage that it became dangerous.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), when he would send Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) to join an army,
he would sent would with him letter to the leader of the army and he would say;
I am sending you Al-Bara'a Ibn Aazib(ألبراءإبن عازب)
but I am telling you do not appoint him as a leader over anyone because he would destroy them.
فَإِنَّ هُمْ اَهْلَكَ مِنَّ الْمَهَلِكْ
They would perish under his leadership,
if you appoint him on anyone he is gonna, they are all dead.
In the Battle of Al-Hadeeqa(ألحديقه) against Musailmah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة الكذاب)
the Muslims were surrounding this fortress and they were unable to get in
and the enemy was hitting them from above, the archers were striking Muslims,
Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) said: Just throw me in! Throw me! throw me in.
So, they put him on a shield and he was sitting on the shield
or standing on the shield and then they raised him up with their spears,
until he reached over the wall and he just jumped
and what he is jumping over?
An ocean of soldiers as far as you can see.
But Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) when he came down, when they looked up they saw a bird
falling down from the sky, they just ran away.
He succeeded in opening the gates, he opened the gates and Muslims came in and that is how they won.
That was how they won.
But he came out with eighty injuries in his body, eighty injuries.
So, Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) was a man that nothing could stop him.
So, Muslims went to him on the day of Tastur(تستر) and they said: Ask Allah to give us victory.
So, it was getting so tight and difficult that they wanted Allah to give them victory.
So, they went to Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) and said: Make Dua(دُعَا) for us.
Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) said: "O Allaah! Grant us victory and give me Shahada(شهادة),
Grant us victory and give me Shahadaa(شهادة) and Allah accepted both".
They were given victory and he was granted Shahada(شهادة).
The Persian Empire had an emperor Kisra(كسرى) and then under him, were kings.
So, he had different states, this was a huge empire.
And each state was ruled by a king.
One of these states or kingdoms was ruled by Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان).
Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان) was captured after the battle of Tastur(تستر).
Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان) before he gave himself up, placed a condition on the Muslims
that only Umar(عُمَر) decides his fate.
Otherwise, I am not going to give myself up.
So, they agreed.
They carried him to Madina and they had him wear clothes that he would wear as a king.
So, they take him into Madina with his crown full of jewelry, gold
and they go and looking for Umar(عُمَر).
They said: Where is Umar(عُمَر)?
They said: He was in the Masjid(مسجد) meeting with a delegation that came from Kufa(كوفه).
They went to the Masjid(مسجد) they didn’t see anyone, so they came out.
And they went around looking, so some kids playing in the streets of Madina said;
"What's wrong with you, looking right and left as if you are lost?"
They said: Where is Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)?
They said he is in the Masjid(مسجد) sleeping.
They go back to the Masjid(مسجد) and they find him sleeping in a corner of the Masjid(مسجد) alone
wrapped in his Thaub(ثوب).
So, they walked up to Umar(عُمَر),
Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان) said: Where is Umar(عُمَر)?
They said this is Umar(عُمَر).
And they said: Be quiet because he is a sleep.
He couldn’t hold back, he said: Where are his guards?
They said: He doesn’t have any guards.
He said: He doesn’t have any clerics the chamberlains, no one, advisors, they said: No.
And by now people were gathering in the Masjid(مسجد) not to see Umar(عُمَر)
but to see Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان).
Because of the clothes that he was wearing, a king from Persia came.
While Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) the Khalifah(خليفه) is sleepingin the Masjid(مسجد) nobody goes there
the kids are playing in the streets.
So, they all came in and because of the commotion, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) woke up.
And when he saw the Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان).
He said: Is that the Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان)? They said: Yes!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
O Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان), what made you do what you did?
Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان) would make an agreement, and then break it.
Make an agreement, then break it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: What made you do what you did?
Deceiving us one time after another.
Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان) responded by saying: O Umar(عُمَر), Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين).
I fear, if I speak you would kill me.
He said: No! I won’t, carry on speaking.
He said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), I am very thirsty.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Bring him some water.
So, they brought him water in a cup.
He held the cup in his hand and said;
Even if I were to die because of thirst, I wouldn’t drink out of that thing?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Bring him a better cup..
So, they brought him a better vessel.
They brought him Allah Ho Alam(ألله أعلم), what it was made up of Wood or something.?
It was something that he saw, it's very cheap and how could you drink out of this,
I'd rather die to drink out of this thing.
So, they brought him a better container or cup or whatever.
They said: Alright drink from this.
He held in his hand and his hand was shaking.
He said: Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), I fear that you would kill me,
If I drink this water.
He said: Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), I fear that you would kill me.
He said: I am not going to kill you, until you drink that water.
Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان) held the cup and he spilled all the water in it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Bring him some more water.
He said: Don’t bring me any water because I am going to drink any.
O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) you have given me, your word of peace,
you have granted me security.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: "No! I didn’t".
He said: Yes! you did! He said: You are not going to kill me,
until I drink the water and I am not going to drink it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You tricked me,
"خَدَعْتَنِيْ"
But I am not going to be tricked by a non-Muslim.
Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه said: O Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين).
Actually Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: No! I will kill you, I will kill you.
Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) said: No! Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) you did grant him security.
You did say that you are not going to kill him, until he talks
And you said: You are not going to kill him until he drinks,
so you did actually give him security."
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I am not going to be deceived by him,
this is the man, who killed Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) and killed Al-Majda’ah(مجزأة).
The Muslims said: Well Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين) you have granted him peace.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab said: I am not going to be the one, who is tricked by non-Muslim.
Al-Hurmozan(ألهرمزان) said: Then I am gonna become a Muslim,
‘أشهد الله اله الا الله و أشهد أن محمد رسول الله
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You are free and he lived in Madina
and he was receiving a salary of two thousand Dirhams(درهم) from the Khalifah(خليفه).
This was one of the kings of Persia, who has deceived the Muslims killed many of them
played games with them but they kept to their word
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) had to let him go.
The Persians were now gathering in another location in Al-Nahwand(ألنهوند).
Now Nahwand(ألنهوند) is not a plan land, it is a city surrounded by mountains.
So, it's very well protected.
But now they are mobilizing an army similar to the army of Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية).
An-Nauman Bin Maqran(النعمان بن مقرن) was appointed by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
as his governor over Cuscar(كسكر).
An-Nauman Bin Maqran(النعمان بن مقرن) sends a letter to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) saying;
There is a young man standing next to the prostitute, who is very beautiful
and she is putting on perfume and she is trying to seduce this man to commit Zina(زنا).
That young man is myself and the prostitute is Cuscar(كسكر).
What he meant by that is, you have put me in a situation, a governor over this place
it is a Fitnah(فِتْنَه), it is a Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and I don’t want to have anything to do with it.
And he said in the letter, please remove me from my post
and sent me out Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) to fight in Jihad(جهاد).
Now I hope that what he said was clear, you don’t get wrong understanding of what he meant.
And this was an analogy that he was giving, this town Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is like a prostitute
and you have a young man and this woman is trying to seduce him,
so he is saying to Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), remove me out of Cuscar(كسكر),
I don’t want to be part of this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), a leader over people and power,
he doesn’t want all of that send me Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), appointed him to lead the army that will fight in An-Nahwand(ألنهوند),
you want to go Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) here,
you are the leader of the army that would fight against the Persians in Nahwand(ألنهوند).
The Muslims fought that battle and they won,
and An-Nauman Bin Maqran(النعمان بن مقرن), because of his sincerity
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, chose him and make him to die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Because Shahadah(شهادة) is not that something that you can easily get,
it is something that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ chooses,
ويتخذا منكم شهداء
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says, in Al-Imran(ألعمران)
"He chooses among you"
it’s a selection process and it is Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ who selects because it’s a such a great honor.
They sent a letter to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) saying that
Shuhada(شهداء) are so and so and the others, that you do not know.
The said: There are some others who died you do not know them.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) cried and he said: Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ knew them so well,
that He choose them to die as Shuhada(شهداء),
so what does it matter if Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), doesn’t know them.
Why would they need Umar(عُمَر) to know them?
If Allahعَزَّوَجَل knew them so well and love them so much that He choose them for this.
This was the battle of Nahwand(ألنهوند).
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ says,
فَارِسُ نَطْحَةٌ , أَوْ نَطْحَتَانِ ثُمَّ لا فَارِسَ بَعْدَ,
وَالرُّومُ ذَاتُ الْقُرُونِ كُلَّمَا هَلَكَ منھا  قَرْنٌ ظھر لھا قرن آخر
أصحاب صخر و بحر هيهات هيهات ھم الناس هم أصحابكم مَا دام فِي الْعَيْشِ خَيْرٌ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: With Persian Empire it would be one knock or two knocks
and then there would be no empire after that, but with the Romans,
whenever you break one of their horns another horn will grow in its place.
Whenever you break one of their horns another horn will grow in its place.
They are people who can fight on land and on sea and in mountains
and they will carry on fighting you until the Day of Judgment.
According to this Hadith(حديث) with the Persian Empire there will be two knocks
two major battles, there are many other skirmishes other battles two major battles
Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية) and Nahwand(ألنهوند) and then the Empire is over.
So, even though the fighting carried on
before Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية) and after Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية) and after Nahwand(ألنهوند)
but the Empire fell apart.
It was Al-Qadissiya(ألقادسية) then Nahwand(ألنهوند) and then Empire ceased to exist.
And it ceased to exist until the day of Judgment.
However, with Roman Empire as we will see whenever, Muslims defeat them in one place
they would show up in another
and that’s why battle with the Romans carries on until the Day of Judgment.
So, after Nahwand(ألنهوند) what happened was
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) allowed his armies to go into the lands of Persian Empire.
Now, when we talk about Persian Empires it's not All Persian people.
The Persian Empire was an empire that included many nationalities,
the Kurd(كرد) lived under it, the Turks lived under it and the Turks are different nations.
So, it was very vast empire.
And probably some of the nations of India lived under Persian Empire.
So, now it's called
"الانسياح في بلاد العجم"
The spreading in the land of Al-Ajam(ألعجم)
and a you have battles like Hamdhan(همدان)
and this was the first time Muslims fight at Addaylum(أدّيلم),
Addaylum(أدّيلم) was also famous for tough fighters.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was so eager to hear the news.
He received a letter saying that we are fighting against Addaylum(أدّيلم).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was so worried about that he was waiting for some news,
so when a messenger came Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) asked him Abasheer(أباشير).
Are you coming with good news?
Now, are you Basheer(بشير)?
Alright! Basheer(بشير) means good news,
that’s what Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: "Are you Basheer(بشير)?"
but the thing is, Basheer(بشير) can also be a name of person.
So, the man said: No I am not Basheer(بشير) and he mentions his name.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
"ابشيرٌا انت"
Are you coming with good news?
And then the man goes straight and said: Yes, yes, yes!
I am here with a good news, we won against them.
But it shows that Umar(عُمَر) was so eager to know what was happening?
And then Khurasan(خراسان), Khurasan(خراسان) was opened.
Khurasan(خراسان) is also a great land.
Hirat(هرات),
and Hirat(هرات) is in Afghanistan and then, Bilaad Al-Akraad(بلاد الأكراد), the land of Kurd(كرد)s.
So, all of those lands were opened as a result of battle of Nahwand(ألنهوند).
Final lessons, I want to go back to Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر)
and the whole approach of the Muslims to Da'wah(دعوة) and Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
you see I received a few questions asking about whether Islam spread by the sword?
And there is this other question.
If there is no compulsion in religion then why were the battles fought?
I think that, this is the issue that you need to have a clear understanding,
because, you know the Non-Muslim say, that Islam spread by the sword, Is that's true or not?
Let's talk about what happened and then we will make judgment.
The Islamic governments spread by force,
the expansion of Islamic empire was done by force, there is no question about that.
The Sahabah(صحابه) went and fought took over other people land
and that’s how Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه) grew.
However, when they would take over land they would not force people to become Muslims
so there is no compulsion in the religion.
So they wouldn’t go to the people and say,
"You must become Muslim!" because that’s something that we don’t have authority to do.
Religion is something in the heart and the person needs to be convinced.
So, did it spread by force or not.
You know, it could be debated both ways.
I mean the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) spread by force, other lands were taken by force.
Why? Because Sahabah رضي الله عنهم the way they saw it,
is that the earth belongs to Allah and only the rule of Allah should be applied over it.
So, no non-Islamic system has the right to exist
according to the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم and their understanding of the religion
because Rasool Allah ﷺ  says;
أُمِرْتُ أَنْ أُقَاتِلِ النَّاسْ حَتَّى يَشْهَدُوْا أَن لا إله إلا الله
I was instructed to fight the people until they say;
اَشْهَدُوْا أَن لا إله إلا الله وَأَنَّ محمدا رسول الله
Establish Salah(صلاة) and pay Zakah(زكواة),
if they do that they have protected themselves from me.
Now, we sometimes, Muslims try to, for the sake of Da'wah(دعوة),
we try to give an impression that you know no, there is no violence that was used, whatsoever,
The Sahabah(صحابه) were not involved in any fighting, they didn't force
anybody to give up their land or kingdom or whatever
and sometime, we could say things against the Sahabah(صحابه),
things that if the Sahabah(صحابه) heard they wouldn’t be happy.
You know, now I want to look at it as follows;
You see, you are Muslim now, and I am Muslim, how did we become Muslim?
If the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم went to the lands of our forefathers
and they had stall and giving out pamphlets asking us to become Muslims,
I am just telling you an example, just think about it.
And saying please become Muslim,
you know Islam is good religion and it’s a religion of peace
and they are trying to convince our forefathers to become Muslims.
Most likely, the response of our forefathers would be,
they would take tomatoes and throw out at their faces and say go back home.
But the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم did not do that. Sahabah رضي الله عنهم went in with armies
and they went in with dignity and respect of themselves.
They didn’t humiliate themselves when they were giving Da'wah(دعوة).
They didn't knocking on every body’s door and saying please become Muslim.
No the Sahabahرضي الله عنهم would take over the land, take over the government
and then they would go to the Masjid(مسجد), if someone is interested in learning the Islam,
you would find us in the Masjid(مسجد).
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم would not run around, begging people to become Muslims.
That wasn’t something that Sahabah(صحابه) did.
And some of the stories mentioned about Rasool Allah ﷺ that he did so, are untrue.
For example there is story that says: That there was once a very stormy night
lightening and raining, thunders in Makkah, nobody was on the streets of Makkah,
except Rasool Allah ﷺ and he went knocking on the door of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل)
and Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) said: No one would come to me in this hour, except if there is great need.
Then Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) opens up the door and find Muhammadﷺ
in the rain soaked in the rain and he is saying, say;
"لا اله الا الله"
And then Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) shuts the door, that's not true.
Rasool Allah ﷺ respected himself, he had dignity,
Rasool Allah ﷺ, would never put himself in such a situation.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would go and speak to the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) with dignity. He would say:
"لا اله الا الله تفلحوا"
You will be successful.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ didn’t want to be abused, he did not want to be cursed.
Sometime, you think that for Da'wah(دعوة) you need to humiliate yourself
No! Rasool Allah ﷺ didn’t want that, and Rasool Allahﷺ was a very sensitive man.
And when the Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) speaks against him that would affect him.
And that is why Ayaat(آيات) of Qur’an have to come all the time to comfort him.
And what happened to him in At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف) was very upsetting to Muhammadﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ would never belittle himself.
He would never put himself in a situation to be humiliated.
And if that ever happened, it happened without his wish or desire.
And it happened because he didn’t have the strength
but later on when he had the strength in Madina he never did that again.
And the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم the way they do the Da'wah(دعوة),
is they would open up the land of the enemies and would give them three choices.
You either become Muslims or you pay us Jizya(جزية) or we will fight you.
And if you don’t want to become Muslim than you have to pay Jizya(جزية) in the state of submission and subdued.
And Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, would open the Halaqaat(حلقات) in the Masajid(مساجد).
And people would come to them, actually,
you know Sahabah(صحابه) did not have to go around, asking the people to become Muslim.
The people would come to them and the people would say, How can we become like you?
Why? Because the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم had the upper hand
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم practiced what they preached they lived it and that attracted the people to them.
So, that was the way of Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
The Sahabahرضي الله عنهم were not the missionaries traveling from one land to other land with loud speakers talking in the streets
and people are just passing them by and not listening to them.
The Sahabah(صحابه) would never put them in such a situation.
A person doesn’t have to humiliate themselves for the sake of Da'wah(دعوة),
you don’t have to do that.
Why? Because our role is not to convert others.
Hidayah(هداية) is something in the hands of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, He will give it to whomever He wants.
Your role is to give Da'wah(دعوة) in a very respected, dignified way
and your role is to deliver the information and that’s it.
And then you leave rest of it to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was not able to convince his own uncle Abu Talib(ابوطالب).
However, he had people coming from far away like Abu Dhar(ابوزر) coming to give him Baiyah(بيعة).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ asked him where are you from?
He said: From Ghaffar(غفار).
Reputations of Ghaffar(غفار) were gangsters, they would raid caravans in the desert.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Allah brings life, after the dead,
"يهدي من يشاء"
Allah gives Hidayah(هداية) to Whom He wills.
So, Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) when he was talking to Rustum(رُسْتُم)
he was delivering the message as it is, you want to become Muslim it’s good for you,
if you don’t these are the consequences of your actions.
So I am presenting to you the way of the Sahabah(صحابه), don’t take me wrong
and think that what I am saying that no, we shouldn’t do Da'wah(دعوة) the way we are doing it now.
You should carry on doing Da'wah(دعوة) the way you can do now, because
may be this is the only way, you can afford it at this particular moment.
But the thing is, I don’t like it, when people give a wrong impression of what the Sahabah(صحابه) did?
That's the thing,
the way of Sahabah(صحابه) wasn't like that
and their way is the best way and the most successful way,
we do whatever we are able to do, because we might not be able to do it,
the way Sahabah(صحابه) did it, because of some circumstance now.
But we have to have the right understanding of their approach and their method,
so that we don’t end up talking against them.
And why I am saying that because,
you know, I am very proud, if it is the fact, with my ancestors if the Sahabah(صحابه) went by the sword,
killed whoever of my ancestors did not wanted to become Muslims
and told the rest you become the Muslim, otherwise you are gonna pay the Jizya(جزية) and you have no future.
I am very proud of that. Because that saved me.
If the Sahabah(صحابه) went in this other missionary way, may be my ancestors wouldn’t have become Muslims
and now I would have been in the Hell fire.
I would rather, have my ancestors killed, and humiliated
and have them being slaves for the Sahabah(صحابه)
and have one of them clean the shoes of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
right, then be a free man, who will ended up, going to Hell fire.
We need to be happy and proud for what the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم did for us
and the way they did it, is by their swords.
That how they did it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: On the day of Judgment
the poor Muhajireen(مهاجرين) will knock on the gates of Paradise, five hundred years before anybody else.
So, the angels will open the gates and say: How did you get here?
The reckoning is still going on.
The poor Muhajireen(مهاجرين) would say: And what will Allah ask us about?
All of our life, we were fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) carrying our swords on our shoulders.
We didn’t do any business we didn’t have any money spend or make
what would Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ ask us about?
Our life was spent fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So, we owe it to Sahabah(صحابه), we need to thank them for what they did
we pray for them, because of what they did for us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Some people would enter Jannah(جنة) in chains,
Some people would enter Jannah(جنة) in chains,
what does that mean? Rasool Allah ﷺ means that
some people are brought, as prisoners of war, dragged in chains
and then they become Muslims.
So, they are saved from Hell fire but they are dragged to Jannah(جنة) in chains.
That’s how they came to it, Allah Ho alam(الله أعلم)
Some of the questions that I already have.
One or, two of them are from last night.
And one of them is fresh, from this evening,
by the way, our schedule for the rest of the period, as we'll talk about
We're done with the opening of Iraq and Persia we'll move on to the opening of a Ash-Sham(ألشام).
So, this stage now will be purely devoted to the Ghazawaat(غزوات).
And then after that we'll talk about the last moments in the Life of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
A brother had typed five questions for me or sister, but I think I already answered one.
Non Muslims often referred Umar(عُمَر)'s codified as evidence that this swords spread Islam.
How should Muslims respond to this?
So we answered that.
And I think the fifth question is the leader of the Islamic State allowed to listen
to the private conversations of the believers who are at their homes,
Islam places importance on personal privacy.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
"وَلا تَجَسَّسُوا"
Do not spy, do not spy.
So spying is Haram(حرام) all forms of spying is Haram(حرام).
You're not supposed to spy on your friends, you're not supposed to spy on your teachers,
A Muslim is not allowed to spy on Muslim.
Somebody gives you a letter and says: Please deliver to so and so,
you don't go and open it and read what's in it.
You have a sense that your brother is doing some Haram(حرام).
Maybe he's on drugs.
So I'm going to try to investigate the matter and he turn himself into a private investor.
That's Haram(حرام), all forms of spying are Haram(حرام).
You pass next to a house and you know that these people are Muslim and you hear music
and you want to make sure that it's coming from their house
and not coming from the neighbor's house, so you go and eavesdrop.
Spying is Haram(حرام), spying is Haram(حرام).
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
"وَلا تَجَسَّسُوا"
Do not spy.
And this also holds true for Muslim government
and a Muslim government is not allowed to spy on any of its citizens,
unless there is a strong valid reason for doing so, unless there's a threat to the Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه)
and a lot of restrictions will be placed, because of the respect of privacy.
Is one allowed to fast on Friday, apart from five days in Ramadhan(رمضان).
Now if you just pick Friday to fast without a reason, that's not allowed.
However, if it, if it happens to be part of your schedule of fasting, then that's all right,
for example, you fast, the fast thing of Dawood عليه السّلام, which is to alternate.
And it happens to be a Friday. That's all right.
If you're fasting the three days of the month.
The three middle days of the lunar month, and it happens to cross over Friday.
That's also fine.
But you're not allowed to just pick Friday out of nowhere and just fast that day.
If there is no compulsion in religion, why were the battles fought,
again we said it is to establish the law of Allah
because the law of Allah needs to rule over the land.
إِنَّ لْأَرْضَ لِلَّهِ يُورِثُهَا مَن يَشَآءُ مِنْ عِبَادِهِۦ ۖ وَلْعَقِبَةُ لِلْمُتَّقِينَ۝
Land belongs to Allah and Allah will inherited to Allah, whomever He wills
and the end belongs to the believers.
That's why the battles were fought.
How does one perform Tahajjud(تهجد).?
You pray it, in pairs of two.
Can pray as many Rak'at(ركعة) as you want and then after that you close it with Witr(وِتر).
If an atheist comes to you and says give me proof that God exists, what is the proof you give?
You say that you exist.
That's the proof, you're standing in front of me.
Tell tell him that you're busy and you don't really have time to talk about this.
And rather, I have an interesting story to tell you it was on the news today.
There was news of a big ship that sailed out of China.
And it was loaded with electronic equipment,
and it went from Shanghai to Hong Kong, from Hong Kong to Singapore,
from Singapore to Aden from Aden to Alexandria,
and then went through the Mediterranean Sea, and it ended up in Liverpool.
And the amazing thing is, that ship had no captain.
There was no one on board.
The police have proved that nobody loaded that ship with electronics.
They also established through proof that those electronics were not made by any company,
and the ship knew its way all the way to the United Kingdom without being guided by anyone.
And they looked into it, there was no electronic equipment to guide it, nothing on its own.
What will he say?
I think you lost your mind.
Tell him well that's what I think about you.
You claim that we arrived here in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) we were born,
we were nurtured we were raised up, we have everything in the Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) that we need,
air, water, food, and all of that was done by no one.
You don't believe that a ship can sail from one town to another and you want to tell me
that the whole earth exists without having a captain,
you make a big deal of one event that happened in the earth,
you say it's impossible, it must have a captain.
And then you want to say that this universe is managed without a manager.
By the way this example that I quoted, with a few modifications to make it relevant to our time.
This was actually an example
that was originally given by Imam(اِمَام) Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه) to an atheist.
If someone gets an exam result and someone else asks for their grade
and they say it's an A, which is true.
Is this boasting.?
I should've left this question, in last question, because…
it depends on why you're saying it
if you're saying it to boost, then it's boosting if you're saying it for the sake of their information, then it's not.
Because we have faith in the beauty of Islam and the virtues of this Deen(دِيْن),
we can understand the Sahabah(صحابه)s methods of spreading Islam, i.e. the sword,
but how do we explain this to non Muslims in Da'wah(دعوة), people who are looking to argue?
People who are looking to argue, will carry on arguing.
And you shouldn't waste your time with them.
Allah did not tell you to make Islam appealing to everyone
because it won't be appealing to everyone.
If it was appealing to everyone, everybody will become Muslim,
but there will be people in every time that won't be convinced
and there's nothing could do about it.
They just won't like it.
And you're not doing Islam a favor by modifying Islam to fit into what they want to hear.
You give the message, as it is, if this person, if it's fit for it,
they will accept it, their Fitra(فطرة) will tell them, it's right.
If their Fitra(فطرة) is upside down, they will reject it.
Qur'an is beautiful! Do you have any doubts in the beauty of Qur'an. Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
وَنُنَزِّلُ مِنَ الْقُرْآنِ مَا هُوَ شِفَاءٌ وَرَحْمَةٌ لِلْمُؤْمِنِينَ ۙ وَلَا يَزِيدُ الظَّالِمِينَ إِلَّا خَسَارًا۝
We reveal in Qur'an, what is Shifa(شفاع), cure and mercy for the believers,
but it only adds to the misguidance of the oppressors or the wrong doers.
The wrong doers when they read Qur'an, it doesn't bring them closer,
it takes them further away, it's repulsive to them.
Why? Because their hearts, their Fitrah(فطرة), the natural disposition
that they have, they don’t have it anymore, their Fitrah(فطرة) is deformed.
So, you know, be honest and straightforward, but the thing is you need to be polite,
that's the thing, in Da'wah(دعوة) you need to be polite,
but you shouldn't change the content and the example that I like to give is,
as a Daiyah(داعية), imagine that you are in the delivery business,
you know like DHL and UPS and FedEx, Royal Mail Delivery, you're delivering packages.
That is the role of Nabi(نَبِي) and Daiyah(داعية).
The package comes from Allah, your role is to convey it.
"وَمَا عَلَيْنَا إِلَّا الْبَلاغُ الْمُبِينُ"
Your role is to convey it.
So you're carrying this package and you want to deliver it to the person.
The package itself comes from Allah.
Therefore, you have no right to open it and tamper with the contents.
You have to give it as it is, you cannot change any letter, any dot any jot, nothing.
You give it, as it is.
What you can control is the method of delivery.
So rather than banging on their door with a hammer, and then they open their door
and just throw the package in their face and say take it or leave it,
You knock the door, very politely, they open the door, you have the big smile on your face.
And you say, this is for you and you do it with the utmost courtesy.
That is what you can control, and that is Al-Hikmah(ألحكمة)
that is the Hikmah(ألحكمة) in Da'wah(دعوة).
The problem is sometimes we get it wrong, we tamper with the contents.
No, no, no Islam, there's, you know Rasool Allah ﷺ did not fight in his life
he only fought for 19 days that was it.
There's nothing, and it was all defensive and
that’s not true, you are changing the facts.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, he is the one who attacked Makkah,
Rasool Allah ﷺ he is the one who attacked the Roman Empire,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is the one, who attacked the Roman Empire and the Persian Empire unprovoked.
He attacked them when they didn't have such plans to attack him.
So to say that it's all defensive and that's, that's not true, that's not the case.
But the reason why they did it.
In fact, what you can say is that every war on the face of the planet is wrong.
Because every war that is fought today, or yesterday, or tomorrow
is done for the sake of power, greed, love of this world.
The only war that is justified is Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) because that's done for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
That's how you should respond back.
So you should say that the only legitimate wars that were fought in history,
were not World War One or World War Two or the Civil War, or this civil war or the 100 year war
all of those wars are unjustified because they are wars over Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
they are wars over money and wealth, they are wars to serve the interests of the kings.
The only justified wars are the words of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم. That's all! That's it!
Because they were doing it for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So speak the truth.
The truth is so beautiful, you don't have to hide it.
What we're doing is, the person in front of you is holding a rock in their hand.
That's what they believe in.
That's the best that they have, that's a rock.
And you have a diamond, and you're hiding it behind your back,
and you're trying to convince them that what is in their hands is rock and it's no good.
They're not gonna be convinced because they haven't seen anything better.
All you have to do is just show them the diamond,
and they're going to drop the rock and take the diamond.
So, present to them the truth.
This is why it was done, because you can't hide the facts,
they'll go to the books, you know, this is At-Tabri(ألطبري) it is translated to English
and the ones, who translated it are non Muslims.
They have access to information maybe, maybe none of you saw this book before, any of Muslims,
and the Kuffar(كفار) they are the ones, who translated it.
So don't think that you can fool them and tell them
no, no, no, Abu Bakr(أبوبكر) didn't fight any wars, and Umar(عمر).
There was no wars in the time of Al-Khulafah(خلفاء).
They're the ones, who are translating the books for us.
So they have the information.
Don't try to hide it.
Try to mention the reasons why it happened.
There's a reason behind everything if you think about it, there's Hikmah(حكمة) behind everything
that Rasool Allah ﷺ did and the Sahabah(صحابه) did.
Okay, this will be our last question.
After attending the session yesterday.
I dreamt that I was living under Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)'s Khilafah(خِلَافَه) and then Umar(عُمَر)'s.
What could this mean, is it just a reflection of my thoughts?
Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم) it could be a reflection of your thoughts, depending on what you saw in the dream
because it depends on what was happening in the dream,
but regardless of whether it was your thoughts, or whether it was a Roya'a(روية).
I would want to say that
we should all be eager to live under the blessed Shariah(شريعة) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Brothers and sisters you don't know what you're missing because he never tasted it.
We never experienced it in our lives, since the day we were born.
We haven't tried it.
So we're talking about something, it is like a dream for us.
And we don't have an example in front of us to see.
But it is a blessing.
We are deprived of a true living, to make it simply that's what it is, we are not living.
Without living under the Khulafa(خلفاء) and the rule of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, you are not living.
So this is not the life.
So we should pray to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to bring back that blessing,
and we should all be parts of the effort to bring it back,
and we should give up our lives for that because that is the essence of true life.
I mentioned this in the series about Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) an old woman.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) saw her in Hajj(حَجْ) and she wasn't speaking.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: What's wrong with this woman, how come she doesn't speak?
They said; She is fasting from speaking.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) told her;
Oh you woman, this is Haram(حرام), this is not allowed in Islam, you need to speak.
So she responded, she didn't know, who it was, she responded back,
she saw that it's a man who has authority who speaks, because of the Ilm(علم) he has.
So she said something, he responded back to her.
And then she said: O man you're talking too much and you're asking too many questions.
Because he was asking her about why is she doing that, why did.?
That's this over with, I'm talking now what, why, why are you asking me all these questions.
And then she said who are you?
He said I'm Khalifa Tu Rasool Ullah(خليفة رسول الله) Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
when she knew that she said and this was an old woman who lived in Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة).
She said, Oh, Khalifa Tu Rasool Ullah(خليفة رسول الله):
Tell me for how long will this good that we are experiencing today, how long will it last?
Because she knows Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة) she said this good that we living today.
How long will it last.?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
It will last, as long as your Imam(اِمَام)s, make it last among you.
As long as they're applying the rule of Allah, then it will last.
So, these are people who lived both she lived Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة) and she lived Islam
and she wants to know she's an old woman, she wants to know how long will it last.
We never tried it, we never experienced it.
We ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to make us at least live a day in our lives with that blessing.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE